<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>ancient metagenomics | James A. Fellows Yates</title>
    <link>https://jfy133.github.com/tag/ancient-metagenomics/</link>
      <atom:link href="https://jfy133.github.com/tag/ancient-metagenomics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <description>ancient metagenomics</description>
    <generator>Wowchemy (https://wowchemy.com)</generator><language>en-gb</language><copyright>© 2021 James A. Fellows Yates</copyright><lastBuildDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    <image>
      <url>https://jfy133.github.com/media/icon_hub6dbd972940fdff31c6d4775500fc8c9_20277_512x512_fill_lanczos_center_3.png</url>
      <title>ancient metagenomics</title>
      <link>https://jfy133.github.com/tag/ancient-metagenomics/</link>
    </image>
    
    <item>
      <title>A Robust Framework for Microbial Archaeology</title>
      <link>https://jfy133.github.com/publication/2017-04-17-robust-framework-microbial-archaeology/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 17 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jfy133.github.com/publication/2017-04-17-robust-framework-microbial-archaeology/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Open access publication.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>AncientMetagenomeDir</title>
      <link>https://jfy133.github.com/project/ancientmetagenomedir/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jfy133.github.com/project/ancientmetagenomedir/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;AncientMetagenomeDir is a creative-commons licensed community curated resource of lists of all published shotgun-sequenced ancient metagenome or microbial genome-level enriched samples. It is primarily meant to act as a reference guide to help point researchers toward any relevant public data for comparative analysis. It is hoped it will help researchers track growth and development of the field of ancient metagenomics over time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I established this project, lead development, and contribute to the ongoing maintenance of the repository.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first release was published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-021-00816-y&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;Scientific Data&lt;/a&gt; (open access).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>nf-core/eager</title>
      <link>https://jfy133.github.com/project/nf-core_eager/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jfy133.github.com/project/nf-core_eager/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;nf-core/eager is a scalable and reproducible bioinformatics best-practise processing pipeline for genomic NGS sequencing data, with a focus on ancient DNA (aDNA) data. It is ideal for the (palaeo)genomic analysis of humans, animals, plants, microbes and even microbiomes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pipeline is built using Nextflow, a workflow tool to run tasks across multiple compute infrastructures in a very portable manner. It comes with docker containers making installation trivial and results highly reproducible. The pipeline pre-processes raw data from FASTQ inputs, or preprocessed BAM inputs. It can align reads and performs extensive general NGS and aDNA specific quality-control on the results. It comes with docker, singularity or conda containers making installation trivial and results highly reproducible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I co-lead development, and the current maintainer of the pipeline.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The pipeline was published in &lt;a href=&#34;https://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.10947&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34; rel=&#34;noopener&#34;&gt;PeerJ&lt;/a&gt; (open access).&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>SPAAM Community</title>
      <link>https://jfy133.github.com/project/spaam/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <guid>https://jfy133.github.com/project/spaam/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The SPAAM community is a group of researchers focusing on ancient metagenomics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We aim to regularly meet to share knowledge on solutions to common challenges and obstacles that the field faces, with cycling organising committees. We also collectively run projects for the benefit of the whole community.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I established the community, and co-organised the SPAAM2 meeting in 2020. I continue to act as &amp;lsquo;caretaker&amp;rsquo; of the community and help establish new projects and collaborations between researchers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have an open slack channel that can be joined via the link on the website.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
